<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Montreal\'s Mount-Royal</string>
    <string name="title">MOUNT-ROYAL</string>
    <string name="desc">The first European to scale the mountain was Jacques Cartier, guided there in 1535 by the people of the village of Hochelaga. He named it in honour of his patron, Francis I of France. He wrote in his journal: "And among these fields is situated and seated the said town of Hochelaga, near to and adjoining a mountain… We named this mountain Mount Royal."

On one theory, the name of the Island of Montréal derives from Mont Réal, as the mountain\'s name was spelled in Middle French (Mont Royal in modern French). However, Cartier\'s 1535 diary entry refers to "le mont Royal". Another argument, mentioned by the Government of Canada on its website concerning Canadian place names, is that the name Montréal was adopted because a Venetian map from 1556 used the Italian name of the mountain, "Monte Real".[4] The name was first applied to the island and was unofficially applied to the city, formerly Ville-Marie, by the 18th century.

In 1643, Paul de Chomedey, Sieur de Maisonneuve made a pilgrimage to the top of the mountain, in order to fulfill a vow made in the winter season on occasion of a great flood which swept up to the town palisades.[5]

In 1876, land owner and farmer James Swail began planning residential subdivisions on the western slope of Mount Murray, in what is now the Cote-des-Neiges district. In 1906, a large housing development was started in the area, called Northmount Heights, with homes built along what is now Decelles Street by developer Northmount Land Company. Much of this area has since been expropriated by the Université de Montréal.[6]

In 1914–1918, the Mount Royal Tunnel was dug under the mountain by the Canadian Northern Railway, a predecessor of the Canadian National Railway. It is currently used by the AMT\'s Deux-Montagnes commuter rail line.

The area was briefly considered as a candidate for the site of Expo 67, before the exposition grounds were ultimately built on adjoining islands in the Saint Lawrence River.[7]

For the 1976 Summer Olympics, the park itself hosted the individual road race cycling event.[8]</string>
</resources>
